Chris: When planning any project, it’s
essential that all the information
required is captured and documented well
in advance of the projects start date.
This is the starting point for the
projects development as it can be
used to keep all stakeholders aligned
to the achievement of a single goal.
Creating detailed business requirement
documentation can also assist with
budgets and time frames for the project.
Leah: To ensure that the business fully
understands the needs of the project
and are able to define objectives
that are attainable, a range of steps
should be taken during the requirements
gathering process to help define how
to achieve the project’s objective.
Defining the business requirements
can be complex as needed to consider
the tasks and goals of the business
as well as the client’s needs.
Chris: The first step would be to
understand who all the stakeholders
are and what their requirements are.
Leah: Stakeholders are anyone involved
in or affected by the project.
In any project there will be multiple
stakeholders which may include end
users, shareholders, developers,
system administrators, customers,
marketing teams, sales teams, clients
and relevant regulatory authorities.
There will also be a ‘project manager’
and ‘product owner’ who will analyse
this information and work with
the various teams and individuals
to develop the project plan.
Chris: You then need to think about
the types of requirements needed,
most of these can be defined as
functional or non-functional.
Functional requirements are usually
set out in detailed ‘Functional
Requirements Documentation’ [FRD], and
a ‘Statement of Work’ [SOW] gives an
overview of the high-level objectives
and requirements of the product.
Non-functional requirements cover
anything that is not relevant to
a product’s functionality such as
performance, stability, security,
and technical specifications.
Leah: For example, ‘Functional
requirements’ for a website may be the
ability to process payments, whilst a
‘non-functional requirement’ would be
an ‘SSL certificate’ to ensure that
payments that are processed are secure.
There may also be other requirements
such as legal, regulatory or even
additional training for those involved
in the development of the project.
Chris: To make sure the information
within the requirements documents is
comprehensive and covers the needs of
all stakeholders, it needs to be gathered
correctly, this is known as ‘elicitation
activities’ These may include document
analysis, brainstorming sessions,
surveys, focus groups, prototyping,
observations and requirement workshops.
Leah: Businesses my use one or
more different methods to achieve
the level of detail required.
The amount of information for a single
user client may only involve having
meetings, whereas developing software
for wider use will require a much
wider range of elicitation methods.
Chris: During the information gathering
stage it is critical to record the results
of all elicitation activities, such as
a meeting or a brainstorming session.
If not over time information
may become unclear or confused.
This can be done by means of a simple word
document, presentation or spreadsheet,
to sophisticated requirement managements
systems and modelling diagrams.
Initial brainstorming sessions or
meetings with stakeholders could be
done on a whiteboard, encouraging
collaboration and creativity.
Leah: Once the requirements information
is recorded it needs to be reviewed and
analysed, to make sure everything is
clear and concise with no ambiguity.
If needed revisions can be made before
being ready to be finalise and implement.
Chris: The final documentation for
the project will be produced, most
likely by a technical writer who will
provide a Statement of Work [SOW],
Functional Requirements Document [FRD]
and Business Requirement Documentation.
There will also be a range of plain
language documentation produced.
Leah: Once the project starts there may
need to be changes to the requirements
and the ‘requirements documentation’
should show this as the project evolves.
It is vital these changes or new
developments are incorporated, and
stakeholders informed, otherwise
the documentation will no longer
be fit for purpose and the project
could face serious issues or delays.
Chris: When working in an Agile
environment, any changes will be added
to the backlog by the product owner, and
those involved in the project will carry
out backlog refinement at a dedicated
meeting during the current sprint.
Here the product owner and the team
will discuss the existing priorities
as well as any items that have been
added, carry out refinement, and
then prioritise the items accordingly